Podcasting 2.0 for November 6, 2020,
episode 10, now entering phase two.
Friday, once again, dark in Austin, Texas.
Winter is a-coming.
Not one, not two, but three remote feeds
today as we start with the dev down south.
Dave Jones, everybody.
What could go, what
could possibly go wrong?
Three feeds over crazy Wafa.
That's right, that's right.
So we've got Dave, Dave Jones,
and we have two guests with us today
who will be joining us for the show.
We've got Tom and Kevin from
Buzzsprout. Guys, how are you doing?
Doing well, doing well.
Yeah, glad to be here.
All right, excellent.
This is Podcasting 2.0, where we are
shepherding in a new era of podcasting.
And before we really get underway
and we're going to, you know,
kind of do this whole show with Tom and
Kevin and talk about how, you know,
how things are, where we're at with
namespaces and also get a little insight into
their company, Buzzsprout, and,
you know, get their ideas.
Because that's really what we're,
what this has all been about
on podcastindex.social,
where we've really had an amazing
hive mind of ideas and development.
But we have a development of our own.
Dave, you've got some, you've been
kind of in and out the past week.
Yeah, this is like the press release
here for the fact that I've had, I was,
I was COVID positive on Sunday.
Yeah, we got, yes, this just
in, ladies and gentlemen. Yeah.
COVID positive Sunday.
I felt like, I felt like I was floating
above my own body for about three days.
Oh, man.
Yeah.
Yeah, it sucked.
I got, it's like, I went
to bed Saturday, that,
I went to bed Saturday
night, feeling great.
We like, we took the kids out for
the trick-or-treats and all that.
And it was, everything was awesome.
And we had some dinner with friends and,
and I wake up Sunday morning and I
was like, oh crap, I feel horrible.
And by like that afternoon,
I was running a high fever and I got tested
and it was like, yeah, you got Rona.
And it was like, it was about three
days of 102 fever, but I'm on,
but I'm over the hump.
I'm good.
But that's, that's why I was, that's
why I was sort of in and out,
not making much sense or anything on the.
No, you weren't making any sense.
You weren't, you were showing up at odd
hours and I knew what was going on.
That could have gone sideways.
And a couple of times I'm like,
I was going to say, you know,
Dave is taking it easy today.
I'm like, I don't know. I didn't know how
to tell everybody without telling them.
Yeah.
I had no idea.
I was, I was messaging
you in the GitHub saying,
is there a problem with my pull requests?
Why aren't they being accepted?
Yeah.
Why, why are you, why are you lazy piece
of crap not approving this pull request?
But, but it's, it's understandable
because the last thing you need on,
you know, it's like have everyone
ask you, sending you messages, DMs,
how you doing, how you feeling?
Is it true?
Are you dying?
Are you dead?
You know, all that stuff.
Yeah.
I was trying to avoid that.
Cause I was like, well, I'll just figure
out to tell everybody on the show.
And yeah, but I'm, but I'm good.
I'm good.
I'm still like foggy and kind of
weird, weird headed, but I'm on the,
I'm on the, the firm upswing here.
So we're, we beat it.
Nice. Now we're very happy
to have you here, Dave.
I'm happy to be here.
So, so we've got Tom and Kevin from,
uh, from Buzzsprout, uh, who have been,
uh, part of the podcast
index.org project for a while.
Um, they have, uh, one of the larger
hosting companies for podcasts in, uh, uh,
the U S maybe the world.
I'm not sure.
Not sure exactly, uh, what size, but
they, they really been incredibly, uh,
open and helpful and progressive dare,
dare I say in a forward
leaning type of way, uh,
to really move things along
and, and get stuff, uh, yeah,
just get stuff implemented and adopted.
And from, uh, my personal point of view,
as we talked about on the last show, um,
it was, it's really hard when you're in
kind of this catch 22 chicken and the egg
situation where you have, uh,
features coming out and no one can
really test them because, because, uh,
the commercial companies have to
go slower, have to make choices,
have to decide what they're
going to support, et cetera.
Um, but there's really no,
there's no other tools.
And, you know, so I've
been out there stomping my
foot and messing up all
my feeds multiple times.
And finally things are
starting to come into view.
And, uh, and you guys at Buzzsprout have,
have really been very, uh, as I said,
you know, really leaning
forward, moving forward with,
with some of this namespace
adoption, which I'm really great.
Which Dave and I are both grateful for.
Um, but I, I think it'd be great if we
could get a little introduction to, uh,
to the two of you and how you started,
uh, you know, how Buzzsprout got started.
Just any, any background
I think would be good.
Yeah, I'll jump in and then
I'll let Tom tell the story.
Uh, I'm Kevin Finn partnered
up with Tom Rossi.
Gosh, who knows how many years
ago now, probably close to 14.
And I always try to remember how old my
daughter is because she was an infant when
we first started up the company.
Uh, we started in 2006, stumbled
into podcasting in 2009 because, uh,
we were doing like website builder stuff.
And a bunch of people were saying,
Hey, I want to be able to,
I have these audio files.
We're working a lot in
the nonprofit space,
a lot of nonprofit people like
churches and other stuff.
They create a ton of audio
content and they couldn't
figure out an easy way to get it online.
So Buzzsprout was born out of that, out
of us, you know, starting with, uh,
Hey, here are some podcasts.
I'm like, you don't know what
that they're called podcasts,
but they are called podcasts
and here's ways to host them.
And then them coming back and telling
us, well, that's too difficult.
And then us creating help articles for other
people's software and them saying it's
still too difficult.
And us just saying, all right, we got
to make a tool that makes this easier.
And so we got into podcasting, introduced
our existing customers to podcasting.
And then slowly and surely podcasting
kept getting more and more exciting.
And we started getting more
and more interested in it.
And at this point is pretty much
the main thing that we work on.
It's pretty much all we do.
And I want to say, what
was it like 2016, Tom,
2017 podcasting started really exploding.
And we, we launched our own shows.
We started launching a ton of content around
podcasting and have just kind of gone
all in and fallen in love with the
independent open podcasting space.
Yeah.
I like, yeah, that's it.
Go ahead, Tom.
Well, yeah, just that,
that, that's, that's it.
That's how we got here.
I think it speaks a lot to the,
you know, what Buzzsprout is.
It was, it was, came out of a place of making
podcasting accessible to people who it
was not accessible to because they
didn't understand what's an RSS feed.
What is a podcast?
They didn't even know what that was.
And so making it really clear, look,
this is a way for you to get your message
out to as many people as possible,
to the people that, you know, it might
be hard for them to hear from you.
This provides a mechanism for
you to be able to do that.
And that was where we were born out of
and where it continues to drive us today.
Yeah.
What I, what I'd like about the Buzzsprout
story and what I noticed, you know,
I signed up and became a customer and then
you, you kindly refunded me my money.
That wasn't necessary,
but it's appreciated.
And I immediately saw how, and this is
your, the roots of the company, I can,
I understand that immediately now you came
from a place of trying to help people
understand what the hell they're doing
and wound up making tools for it.
But you never stop with
the education part.
And I think that's part of that's your,
your, your Sproutcast, your Buzzcast.
It's a lot of the documentation.
I believe Melissa was, I got an email
from her from, I had a support question.
I get regular emails with
kind of industry stuff.
It's, it's, it's a, it's a role that
I think is very, it's very good.
Is this something that other
companies, other hosting companies,
do they do this kind of stuff as well?
Is this a general role that podcast hosting
companies fulfilled in the ecosystem?
You know, I think it's
a little bit of both.
Yes and no.
I would say that there has
been a bit of, you know,
podcasting is technology and it's
intimidating for people who don't,
who aren't into it and aren't
excited about learning
all the ins and outs of technology.
There are a lot of people who just have a
message that they want to get out to the
world and they need somebody to
help make that easy for them.
And so they're not necessarily interested
in learning how to compress an audio file
or learn how to hook up an audio interface
or learn how to do all this stuff.
But if you can make it fun
and engaging and, you know,
remove those barriers of entry for them,
then they've got a message
that's just as valid
as somebody else who's into all the tech.
They just need a simple
way to be able to do it.
And we think there's a
difference between, you know,
just downloading an app and talking into
your phone while you're driving around in
your car with your friend and somebody who
really wants to put a professional touch
or professional podcast together.
We think there's still an opportunity for
them to be able to do a professional show
and take it seriously,
but not necessarily have to go get a
degree in audio engineering and spend,
you know, $5,000 in tech
stuff to be able to do it.
And so that's where our education stuff
comes in is that we want to lower those
barriers of entry as, you know, to
the question of do other hosts do it?
Some do, some don't.
Some definitely feels like
this is kind of, you know,
they take the approach of, hey,
if you're not all in and you
want to learn everything,
then this might not be
the right thing for you.
You have to control
every little bit of it.
And then there's other
people, you know, like,
like the anchor app is on the other
end of that spectrum, which is like,
just download the app and
talk into your phone.
And then that's a fine podcast too.
So we're kind of in the middle there.
What are your roles in the company?
I'm a, so this is Kevin and I do
more like product development,
like front end stuff.
And then Tom leads our
entire technical side,
which I'll just call it technical side.
Tom will tell you all the details of it.
Yeah.
Tom, what the hell does that mean?
All the goodness.
Yeah.
Dude, he, Kevin's good at dreaming
up stuff and then I make it happen.
That's, that's a better picture.
Oh, that sounds like a
familiar relationship to me.
Tom, me, Dave, Kevin, me, Adam.
Yeah.
Right.
Exactly.
Yeah.
We can commiserate.
I'm familiar with this,
with this relationship.
Except I, I can't, I can't do code if my
life depended on it other than an Apple
script I did 16 years ago.
So.
What is it?
I get very excited when I check
in a commit to the GitHub.
I really want it accepted because I,
you know, I've rarely write code.
And so once in a while I get to
update a document or something.
I'm like, I don't want
to see my book in there.
It's a dope.
It's a dopamine hit.
That's what it is.
So Dave said that y'all, y'all
are like, y'all are mostly,
y'all had organic growth and
y'all are mostly, you know,
I think that's the term you use.
It's mostly podcasts now.
I mean, like, when did you decide or when
did you begin to consider yourself to be a
podcasting company, you know, a company
rather than a web company or whatever,
you know, your origins were?
Yeah.
Well, we launched in, we
launched Buzzsprout in 2009.
And at the time it was just like, it
was like a sister product to this,
you know, our larger product,
which was this content management
system for nonprofits.
And it, Tom, help me
out and remember here,
but I want to say it was within a
year or two that that product was,
Buzzsprout started outperforming
the content management system.
And so it was a pretty easy transition
for us at that point of saying, hey,
this is, we're onto something here.
And at the same time, there were a lot
of new companies popping up in that,
you know, website builder space that
had larger teams and more funding.
And they were doing a really good job.
Tom and I have never been super interested
in solving problems that other people
were already solving really well.
Like we don't just want to
jump into a market just
because we think there's
an opportunity there.
Like we wanted to really get into a space
where we could fill a need that other
people weren't fulfilling.
And so we felt that pull
more in the podcasting space
than we did in the website builder space.
So as soon as the product,
like as soon as the market started justifying
us to be able to move our focus over
to podcasting, we were
super excited to do it.
I think it was definitely exciting
because we have, we have other products,
but Buzzsprout is probably the
most fun to work on because it's
podcasting and we used to just joke.
Like, could you imagine
if one day this pod,
if this product made as much as
our other products and yeah, we,
we were very happy, you know,
when it started taking off.
Cause it's just so much fun to work with.
So, I mean, I'm assuming y'all
have, y'all still have like,
or I'm not going to say legacy.
I hate that term, but y'all still have
other stuff you're trying to support that
isn't as non podcast related
to the company though.
Right.
Yeah.
We have other products.
The reason I ask is because
that's, that's hard.
I mean, it's hard switching, you know,
it's hard switching between two
different, you know, two, three,
four different code bases.
I mean, that's, that's a challenge.
I can feel your pain on that.
I think it's interesting, especially
when you're talking about podcasting.
Kevin said this, I don't know,
a couple months ago and,
and it really resonated with me,
but he was talking about the
fact that we are a product
development company that
got into podcasting.
Like our core competency is being able
to take complicated things and making it
accessible to people,
making it understandable.
And all of our products,
they're all in that space of,
of making things easy for people,
helping them do those
things rather than being a
podcasting company that
got into technology.
You know, we were, we were a technology
product company that got into podcasting.
What other products do you
have just from my edification?
They're all, they're all over the place.
So we have our content management system,
which believe it or not, we still have,
I think we have less than
a hundred customers,
but we still have people on that product.
We have one that's in the time
tracking space called tick,
which is time tracking for people
to track time against budgets.
We have one in the medical
space called stream care,
which helps physicians run
their own in-office pharmacy.
And we have donor tools, which is a
nonprofit donor management system.
Wow.
You guys like a, like a
garage full of solutions.
Yeah.
We have a lot of different
products there, you know,
all products that we've rubbed
up against that we're like, man,
I think we could build something.
Here that would really add
value and, and solve something,
make it easy where other people
are saying it's too complicated.
It's too hard.
We're going to get in there and we're
going to, we're going to make it easy.
And you can see it in Buzzsprout, but you
can see it in these other areas as well.
And how do you, how do you, how do
you market your podcast services?
Do you, is it, do you just have set budgets
and you have a number of places where
you buy a space or, I mean, I'm
curious how you get the word out.
Is it word of mouth?
Well, let me, let me tell
you where we started
and then let Kevin tell you where we are.
Today, because when we first
started, it was all word of mouth.
So we were working with people who
were trying to solve that problem.
So a lot of them were coming from our
content management system and they were
struggling with it, but then
they started telling people.
And then as they told people, it
was just, it was just organic.
And we really didn't, we really
didn't do a lot at all in to, to,
to grow the product.
But then maybe what Kevin,
maybe three, four years ago,
we started taking it very seriously
and actually put in the work to grow.
So, and then Kevin can kind of
tell you how that's worked out.
Yeah.
So, and we touched on this
a few minutes ago, but our,
our main path of growth has been
through educational resources.
So whether we, whether it be a blog post or
a video we put online or a podcast or an
online course that we
make available for free,
we want to educate people and
get them excited about space.
And remove those barriers
or entry for them.
And then they're, um, you know,
as soon as they get to the point where
they say, okay, we're ready to go.
I mean, they could choose us or
they could choose somebody else,
but hopefully more times than not,
they remember that we helped them get to
this place and they at least check us out
up against the competition.
So as far as advertising
goes, we do some paid ads.
Uh, I mean, I would love to get more and
more out of that stuff because it just,
the more ad tech just keeps
getting creepier and creepier,
but it is a good channel for us.
It's clear.
We, we pay for advertising.
We pay to, to advertise Buzzsprout.
We don't make money off of, you
know, putting ads in our product.
Right.
Got that.
Um, it reminds me of digital ocean,
like what you're talking about.
It's like, uh, when, if you, if I go to
Google right now and just search for,
uh, anything like how to, uh, install,
uh, some product on, uh, Ubuntu 20,
not like nine times out of 10, a digital
ocean instruction, a tutorial article.
It's probably going to come up.
And it seems like, like being the, the
tutorial people or the help people,
it does, it really does create a funnel
into your product because you're helping
people you're, you're onboarding them
into the thing that they want to, to,
to do to begin with.
But then you have this side effect
of being able of saying, Oh, well,
while you're here, you might as well
just, you, you know, our product is,
you know, is available as well.
I mean, it's a great, it's sort of a
great route to take is, uh, is, I mean,
having followed the hosting
situations from day one
and just bandwidth and
storage was a huge problem.
And I think it might've
been Libsyn who think
first was coming out with very low prices.
Um, can you really make money
off of this business is,
is ultimately the question I want to ask.
And has that changed throughout the years?
Yeah.
I think Tom, you want to take this one?
Sure.
Yeah.
Uh, I mean, it's, it definitely
costs money to host and that's what,
what people have to understand,
um, is that bandwidth and storage,
even though it is much more affordable
these days than it was, you know,
10 years ago, uh, it
still costs something.
And I mean, we were just talking about
some of our podcasters we lose money on
because they use so much bandwidth.
They have episodes that go
viral and things like that.
It's like even at, uh, a $12 a
month, uh, subscription, you know,
we lose money on those.
Um, and so when people say things like,
well, you know, it should be free.
You're like, well, it costs something.
So somebody has got to pay for it.
So how is that, how is it going to happen?
How, how is that, you know, uh, how
is that exchange going to take place?
And so from the very beginning, we've
always said, let's just be straight up.
Like you pay a monthly fee for
a certain amount of storage.
And if you look at our buzzsprout pricing,
we price based on hours of content.
Again, cause you know,
we're targeting people
that they don't understand
a gigabyte of how long is a gigabyte?
And so we say, well, it's
so many hours and we don't,
they don't have to worry about encoding.
Uh, so that way we can predict how
much storage that will actually be.
Cause when they upload it to us,
they can upload a wave and we'll go ahead
and we'll automatically encode it and
optimize it and do everything
that needs to happen.
And, um, most of our people don't
understand most of our entire,
there's entire seminars that teach
people how to do that stuff.
And you guys are just doing it for them.
That's nice.
Right.
And so like Kevin was saying earlier,
when you talk about other hosts,
that's always been our
position of if you care,
if you're the guy that wants to
be able to go and, Oh, I want to,
I want to actually edit my file directly.
And I don't want you touching it
and all those kinds of things.
Um, you know, we have some ways to
accommodate that with buzzsprout,
but we might not be a good fit because
you sound like somebody who you're not,
you don't want a simple solution.
You want to actually
go build your own XML.
Like if you want to learn XML, buzzsprout's
not going to be a good fit for you.
So how did you, and by the way, um,
Dave and I are big believers in the
days of free coming to an end and this,
it ha it has to end eventually.
Um, you know, so just looking at the
incredible benefit we get from podcast
index.social, you know, there's,
there's a couple of people who,
who do Mastodon hosting.
Uh, and I found this kid in, I think
Denmark or Norway and he said mastodothost,
you know, and for a,
for a small instance with a hundred
people or so it's nine euros a month.
And so I set it up on that and then
we need a little more and, you know,
we didn't need some search enabled.
And so I don't know, now it's 29
euros, which is fine, but you know,
you get service, uh, and you can
do whatever you want, but yeah,
free has, it's kind of over.
I think people are seeing the issues
and I didn't even, I had no idea how,
uh, prevalent tracking is
in podcasting with, um,
all kinds of shenanigans
that are going on.
It's really, it's really quite amazing.
If you, if you think about it, you're,
you're forced into that, right?
Because they're trying to figure out
if we're going to offer this for free,
we've got to figure out how to make money.
And so you as the podcaster have no idea
what strategies they're going to try to
employ to monetize your content.
And that's the cost of
you getting it for free.
Hey, Tom, Tom, tech guys
can't talk that smart.
You're supposed to be in the back, man.
You can't talk smart stuff like that.
That's not how it works.
Yeah.
I don't know if you guys saw the article,
but it was a couple of years ago before
anchor got acquired by Spotify and the CEO
posted a blog post on medium or something.
And he was talking about the, how is anchor
able to provide these services for free?
And what does it really cost
them to host a podcast?
And they were saying, you know,
for the typical anchor podcast
that costs them, I don't know.
I mean, it was ridiculously low.
It was like, you know, a dollar a
month or something to host the show.
And that's why they're
able to do it for free.
But the reality was, I mean,
I just felt like as I was reading that it
was the most disingenuous thing I had read
in a long time because you
might be talking about a
typical podcast that
doesn't have a large reach.
And that you're talking about
the bandwidth cost alone.
That is like 5% of the equation.
I mean, you have staff, you have
programmers, you have support people,
you have server costs, you have an office,
you've got healthcare, you've got taxes.
Like there's so much that goes into
running a business that it's not just a
bandwidth is one bill out of a
hundred that come in every month.
And so to boil it down to that and to try
to make people believe that paying for
hosting is not worth it because the bandwidth
bill is only a dollar a month for a
typical show is, is just terrible.
Like you've got to make
up that money somewhere.
And they had raised millions of dollars and
then they sold for millions of dollars.
And there's a whole nother
business that's going on there.
And it's like attention economy stuff
and profiting off of, you know,
your listener base and,
and tracking people.
And they are thinking, hey,
let's build a huge audience.
And at some point we'll figure out how to
monetize the creations of other people and
the listeners that they attract.
It's not a dollar a month, guys.
No, that's, that's an
interesting, like, I want to,
I want to ask you about Anchor
specifically because they, um,
I was looking at just the
hosting stats, just among, uh,
how many feeds each hoster
has and that kind of thing.
And I mean, a lot of it's just,
you know, estimates, I mean,
none of this stuff is, is, is hard
science here, but I mean, like clearly,
you know, clearly Anchor is the, you know,
the big behemoth as far as
the number of podcasts.
But is there any sense of how much of that
is garbage and how much of it is what you
would consider just like a
legitimate real podcast?
I mean, I I'm looking at, I don't
know, is it like 650,000, uh,
shows or something like that.
And I mean, is it half,
is half of that garbage?
I don't know.
You get, do you have any sense of that?
Yeah.
I mean, there are people who are trying to
answer that question, like, uh, Daniel J.
Lewis.
I love, I love that.
We have this eclectic group of people who
are finding feeds and sorting through
stuff and sleuthing.
I mean, this is, I'm sorry.
I just needed to say how much I love that.
We got everybody on podcast index.social.
It's a, it's a gang, man.
I like it.
Yeah.
So he's, he's doing some great work
and trying to figure out like,
how do we define an active podcast?
Because we know that there's, you know,
hundreds of thousands of people who are
probably downloading that anchor app and
loaded it up and said, Hey,
this is my first podcast.
I hope, uh, you know,
everyone enjoys the show publish
and then they never come back.
Is that really a podcast?
Count that?
Well, it's listed in the
Apple podcast directory.
So I guess we did count it.
I don't know.
And so he seems like every,
it seems like every
anchor podcast that gets
created is automatically listed in iTunes.
Yeah.
Unless they, unless they
copy somebody else's.
Until they, until they
do the locked feature.
I mean, come on.
Yeah, sure.
Yeah.
Until they implemented it.
Day one, right?
Well, well, that's probably
a good segue into, uh,
the namespace and how you guys heard
about podcast index.org and, um,
you know, what, just what you think
in general of the project and, um,
and your thoughts and ideas.
Well, I'll tell you,
we have been internally clamoring for
something like this for a long time.
We, we've, we've had multiple
conversations about doing it ourselves.
And the problem with somebody like us
doing it is that we are not, I mean,
we're, we're not independent, right?
And so anything that we do, any
innovation that we try to do with inside,
inside of a feed is not for
the benefit of the community.
At least that's not how it's
viewed from our competitors.
It's, it's, it's us trying
to leverage, you know,
something in the feed for a competitive
advantage for our platform,
which isn't necessarily
aligned with our intentions,
but that's just the way
that it's perceived.
And that's not to say anything
negative about our competition.
Like we would have a hard time in
terms, you know, if they did something,
we'd have a hard time just being like, Oh,
that's actually good
for the open community.
Let's jump on board.
And so there's been this
struggle to innovate
because we're all
competing with each other.
And even though we see each other at
conferences and we're all friendly and
everything at the end of the day,
we still are trying to build the best products
and then leverage those advantages to
get the most customers.
And so to have someone like you
guys come along and say, Hey,
we're not a hosting company.
We're not an app company.
We are just people who care about the
space and we care about it remaining open.
And we care about having a
platform for free speech.
We care about all these good
things that everyone can agree on,
regardless of whether you're host A
or B or app C or D doesn't matter.
Let's come together and innovate.
Because if we don't,
so these platforms are going to continue
to move and then we're going to lose
podcasting to these walled gardens.
And that's not good for anybody.
Nobody wants that.
Right.
And that's what's happening.
That's what we're super excited about.
And I, the only thing,
the only question I have at
this point is why aren't there,
why isn't everybody jumping in here?
Why isn't every podcast host
participating at the level that we are?
I can tell you that I can, well, I
can't, I can't speak definitively,
but I can tell you that for really
the only pushback that we've gotten,
I think is from.
Sort of gatekeeper mentality.
There's, there's a sense of, and I get it.
I mean, here's a, here's just, I mean,
even though Adams clearly, you know,
been in, you know, pod, you know, in
the podcast space for forever and,
you know, invented it.
But it's, there is a
sense of just a couple
of guys coming in and who are these guys?
I mean, like we, we have all, we have
boards and standards bodies and,
you know, association,
trade associations and all this
kind of stuff, you know, that.
Those all sound like innovator killers.
Yeah, it's exactly right.
And, you know, we've, we've come up against
that in the pod, you know, I'm sure,
you know, I mean, you've talked
through email privately, Tom, about,
you know, people that have said,
you know, come in and men.
Oh, you should do this, you know,
you should have a standard that
should be rigorous and, you know,
all this kind of stuff.
And it's like, well, I mean, standards
bodies are, are fine, but, and, and they,
but we're not building HTML six here.
I mean, this is just some podcast tags and
it really shouldn't take 10 years and a
501c3 and all this kind of stuff just to
get, just to get maybe 10 podcast tags.
And this was really a revelation for me
as we were going down this path and I,
and all of a sudden I just saw
the problem, you know, and,
and I started looking
into, I've been at one,
I was on the original RSS
board and that, you know,
there was never a meeting or anything.
It was just a bunch of names
and okay, fine, whatever.
And I'm sure I got removed
without, without them telling me,
but it just never made any sense
why nothing had moved forward.
And then when I really started to look,
I understood that Apple had
become this behemoth and this is,
I take that upon me, although,
you know, it is what it is.
And 2020 is hindsight.
I gave them the index.
They kind of became the default app
in general, but also the index.
And so they have two pieces of the pie.
They're not just an app
and without Apple support,
and they have no reason to
do much more innovation.
They really don't from
a business perspective.
And I think a lot of hosting
companies were suggesting things and,
but until an Apple said, yeah, okay,
we're, we're on board and now it's worse.
Now it's, it has to be Apple and Spotify.
And that's when, when Dave and I went
like, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
This is backwards.
Come on.
We're taking the index back and,
and we're going to, you know,
we're going to set up something that is
for all intents and purposes immutable.
This is something that should unify all
of us, all of us that are, that have,
you know, skin in the game
for independent podcasting,
whether we're hosts or players
or anything like this.
We should all be excited about
an independent organization,
helping us innovate together because
we can innovate quicker than,
than any one of these, you know,
behemoth companies that are
beholden to, to shareholders.
And so when you go and you
look at what we've been
able to do in a short
period of time and yeah.
Okay.
So there's not a, not every player supports
it and not every podcast host supports
it yet, but we can
quickly do these things.
Let's do that.
You know, let's make a
difference in this industry
much quicker than any of
these other guys can.
Yeah.
I don't know if y'all see, I mean,
just having looked at some of the stuff
that is coming out with, you know,
with the apps that are linking up on
podcast index.social that everybody is
implementing the things like chapters
and transcripts and now soundbites.
People are implementing this stuff into
their apps and then they're posting
screenshots and they're linking up
where you can go and test them.
And just even with those few, two or
three tags, it's gotten exciting.
It's, it's beautiful.
Yeah.
I mean, like the, it's such
a rich, uh, experience.
I mean, like you can't get, you, you
can't get the experience that you get in,
uh, in pod, uh, pod friend or
hyper catcher or pod verse.
Or, uh, I mean, like you forget the
one that was posted last night.
Somebody posted a pod bay.fm pod bet.
Yeah.
Like those things you can't get that
experience in the silo ads right now.
They're not, they're not doing that.
And you know, what's happened?
Something really cool happened.
And I, and I think it was partially
between hyper caster and pod friend.
And, you know, cause I started posting
chapters and they really became,
it became more like a slideshow.
So not just, not just the
place where, you know,
you tap on something to go to a time
code, which is something I despise.
I want people to be forced to listen
to everything I say and no shortcuts,
but now it's like, now I can put a
picture up and then there's a link.
And then, you know, you can click
through to the link and it's more like a
multimedia presentation,
which once we figure it out,
can be completely crowdsourced.
I mean, that's, that's,
you know, it's fantastic.
We're using one guy's app, David with
hypercatcher and hypercatcher studio.
So I can author the chapters in there.
People can use his app
to suggest chapters yet.
It works over here on pod friend.
I mean, I don't think we've
had that even in 16 years.
Yeah, that's hugely significant.
And exactly what you just said about the
ability for the open podcast space to
innovate and do things is, I mean,
it's been really, really hard.
Everybody who's building stuff.
I mean, it's not easy to build this stuff.
Sometimes it takes large teams.
There's a lot of money.
There's a lot of risk that goes into it.
And then it's, we've talked
about this plenty of times.
It's the chicken or the egg problem.
And so who is going to, you know,
lay the first egg and hope that a chicken
comes along and sits on it or whatever,
wherever that analogy goes from there.
I like it.
Yeah.
For years, we could have put
tons of stuff into the RSS tag.
But again, that would take us time.
It would take us development time.
It would cost us money to do that.
And also, if there's no apps, if there's
no apps out there to use it, I mean,
you can't even get it.
I mean, I have 800,000 to a
million downloads a week.
And, you know, so when I mess
something up, it's monstrously cool.
I mean, people have double episodes.
They've got wrong album art showing up.
And, you know, that's
all on me because I just
hack away and I'll get
it right eventually.
And people know me by now.
And I spend a lot of time on Twitter
saying, oh, could you please resubscribe?
But once you bring users in and you guys
are going to be, will be, you know,
amongst the first to have
users that are taking
advantage of a lot of
these authoring tools.
And there's others out there.
I mean, for sure, we've
got, I think, Castapod,
who is kind of like a self-host situation.
They're implementing tags.
You know, I think the namespace has been
implemented by three of the locked tag,
which is small, but it
recognizes the namespace.
You know, I think that's a big deal.
Yeah.
What is on your roadmap?
Well, let's get into the
roadmap in one second.
I would say, you know, what I,
what I'm excited about is that there is
the people who are participating the most
right now in what's
happening in the podcast
index are smaller apps and smaller hosts.
We're one of the bigger
ones that are jumping on.
But again, because I think we've
just been wanting this for so long.
We're super excited about it.
And we have the team size that
we're just able to do it.
But for some reason, some of the larger
hosts are being a little bit more reluctant.
And so maybe they're waiting to see, you
know, what's the adoption on this stuff.
So this is just a shout out to
anybody listening to the show.
Like you, if you host with somebody,
a larger host or somebody who's
not on board with this stuff,
you need to reach out to them and let them
know that you want to use these tags for
your show, that you're excited about.
Not just like the locking tag and
things like protecting your show,
which is super important, but also,
hey, I need transcripts in my show.
I need chapter markers in my show.
I need, I want, you know, host
and guest images in my show.
All the stuff that's happening right now.
I don't know what's going on
with some of the big guys,
but it seems like they're sitting
back and waiting for, who knows?
Or maybe we finalize the tag at
the 15th and then they jump in.
You know, about in 1981, there was a
campaign that was similar to this.
It was, it went like this.
Call up your cable company
and say, I want my MTV.
That's true.
Yes.
That's it.
I love that.
And you know what's great about this?
This is the part that can't be overlooked.
Because right now, you know,
I've sent a tweet out once or twice for
people to do some chapters in Hypercatcher.
And, you know, so I get some,
get some feedback through there.
But once you have cool new features
that you're authoring as a podcaster,
what you're going to do
is you're going to say,
and this is what I fully intend to
do once I have the workflow down,
is on my show, I'll say, hey,
check out these five apps.
Or I've made a page.
You can, or go to this
place on podcastindex.org.
And you can see all these new features.
Now, this drives listeners who say,
oh, either they don't care or, oh,
okay, this is nice.
And maybe they like the app
and some other features.
And that, in turn, drives
them towards that.
Because I've been in this
game from the beginning.
I get, like, the chapters thing.
Comic strip blogger has been,
I've known him for a long time.
He is my personal troll and CIA handler.
I'm not quite sure which comes first.
And he has been telling
me I'm an idiot for not
doing chapters for years
and years and years.
People will hound podcasters to
add features, to author features.
I never saw the benefit of it
because it couldn't be crowdsourced.
And now, of course, I have that.
So it fulfills itself.
The marketing of these features,
if they're worth their salt,
will propagate very quickly.
So, you know, when you get podcasters
knocking at your door saying, hey,
I'd like these features,
that's the time to listen.
And I think that's going to happen in
kind of a snowball fashion, you know,
once we get some more things implemented.
You know, these chapters, which
you guys are already doing, right?
You already have chapters and captions.
We've had chapters for years in the MP3.
Yeah, right.
And so now we've included
them in the RSS feed using
the spec that was adopted
in Podcast Index.
Yeah, beautiful.
But I think what gets me excited
are the things that are new,
like transcripts are brand new.
Whereas you could do chapters
before, transcripts are brand new.
So when you go and you look in, like,
Podcast Addict or Podfriend or one of these
guys that's actually showing the words
while you're listening.
It's fun.
Yeah, that's amazing.
And when you look at the soundbites,
the idea that Kevin really put forward,
this idea that the podcaster can say, hey,
if you're thinking of
listening to this episode,
here's a 30-second clip that might
sell you on why you should, you know,
listen to the whole thing.
Something like that, it
can be a massive feature.
But it takes the host, the podcaster,
and the app working together
to make that happen.
Yeah.
The soundbite idea is
hopefully a solution to, well,
to prevent us from having to go
down the road of algorithms.
Like people talk about podcasts
having a discoverability
problem all the time, right?
And I feel like that's just, I mean,
that's just asking for trouble, right?
Like if you want somebody
to solve discoverability,
they'll build an algorithm
that'll solve discoverability.
But you know what it's going to do?
It's going to figure out what you're
susceptible to and what holds your interest.
And it's going to start feeding you
through that same garbage all the time.
Yeah, totally.
Yeah.
We don't want that.
Didn't Spotify just change the
compensation with their musicians?
I read that, yeah.
Yeah.
And so the idea being,
if there's an algorithm controlling
what's being put in front of you is, hey,
listen to this next.
If there is some dollar attached to it,
then they're obviously going to push the
thing that isn't necessarily the best thing
for you to listen to, but the thing
that's going to make them the most money.
So I love the idea of a
way around algorithms as
a way to solve that discoverability issue.
And so we've seen two versions
of that that I like very much.
One is the, I always forget
the name, Dave helped me,
Cast Coverage, castcoverage.com,
which dumps you into random episodes,
a random spot in the feed.
And I laugh my ass off and from time to
time actually use the pod friender feature
of pod friend, which is like,
it's like a Tinder and literally a podcast
pops up and you swipe left and it's gone.
You swipe right and it's
added to your favorites.
And I've used that a
lot and just looking at
album art and listening to a little bit.
Oh, I'll check that out.
I mean, so discoverability is
taking place in different ways.
I think the biggest thing that we're coming
up against now is how do we make a lot
of these audience participation features,
how do we make them work across apps?
So, because really, you know,
what YouTube has over podcasting is the
chat on the sidebar where everybody can can
jump in and chat along and they've got all
kinds of funky features you can use their
comments that work across the system.
This is where we're lacking and any
centralized silo is always going to have a leg
up initially to be able to provide that.
And I think that's where, to me,
human beings are still great
AI and they will recommend
the right things to the right people.
Or at least your AI and your brain will
know, avoid this guy's suggestions.
Those are the things that I
think we can really excel
at if we figure out some of those issues.
Yeah, I think the algorithm
problem has just never,
you can't solve things
always with an algorithm.
You can't, for instance, there's no way
a music prediction algorithm is there.
I'm a huge Rush fan.
And so there's always going to be this
prediction in the algorithm that says,
oh, you like Rush, so you're going
to like this other power trio.
Well, the fact is, I
don't like any of those.
I mean, there's just
something unique about that
one band that I like
that you can't quantify.
You cannot put it into any parameters
which properly inform an algorithm.
And I think it's the same
way with podcasting.
I heard, I think it was Marco
Arment talking a few weeks ago.
He said, what people follow in podcasts
is not like information or guests
necessarily or blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah.
What they follow are personalities.
So like you, it's like,
I want to listen to Adam's
podcast or I want to listen to,
you know, Kevin's podcast.
It's like you get, you get connected
to where you feel like you have, you,
you feel like you have a connection to
the host and you begin to follow that
person's podcasting.
And like, you can't necessarily quantify
that into any sort of algorithm that's
going to, it's going to make a prediction
engine that, that feels right.
You know, a good AB comparison for algo,
non-algo is Twitter and
podcastindex.social.
So podcastindex.social, although things
are obfuscated from view for you,
depending on who you're following, you
can always pretty much start at the top.
And then eventually you wind
up, oh, I've already seen this.
And then you're done.
Whereas on Twitter, it's like, shit's
popping up from eight hours ago.
It's like, oh, what is this?
It's a reply.
Everything is weighted the same.
It's not, you know, uh, uh, they're
not, it's not threaded properly.
And I find a lot of signal
to, the signals to noise on,
on the Mastodon server is high, man.
I get a lot out of that.
Yeah.
I mean, two totally different
goals of those platforms, right?
The Mastodon server, the goal is to give
people a place to communicate information.
And so I go there and I caught up on
my information and then I'm done.
The goal of Twitter is to keep me
on that site as long as possible.
So like you want to say
profitable way and never end.
Like you will always find
something new to show me.
What are you?
I was just saying that they
want to keep you on the
platform in the most
profitable way, right?
Not only do they want
to keep you on there,
but they want to put the
stuff in front of you.
That's going to make them the most money.
And that's where, that's where that's
fine tuning an algorithm is first.
They're going to get you
addicted and then they
can start turning the
screws to make sure that
the stuff that they're putting in front
of you makes the most money for them.
That's the YouTube philosophy
where they switched from, was it?
Yeah.
Click from, was it like clicks or likes
to engagement time, engagement time?
And that's where like, I don't want to,
I don't even want to argue
the validity of algorithms
being better at finding stuff or not,
because even if they solve
that problem at the end of
the day, the motivation is different.
Like Kevin was saying, the motivation
of YouTube is not to educate you.
It's not to find the content, it's to
keep you on the platform with the,
in the most profitable way possible.
So, um, well then I'll, I'll ask this
question to you specifically then Tom,
uh, like the biggest
to me, you know, clearly we
had, you know, podcast index.
We're doing, we're, we're trying to,
uh, we're trying to do two things.
We're trying to be an independent
directory of podcasts, uh, so that, uh,
Apple is not the center of the universe
and that's not against, you know,
nothing against Apple there, they're,
they've been great stewards of podcasting.
It's just that that it
shouldn't be that way.
It really, it really just shouldn't.
And the, the other thing is running the
API, try to give a small podcast apps,
uh, the ability
to boot up without having to launch 30
servers in a, in a, in a backend somewhere.
So like, those are, those are really
the two goals of the index, um, and,
and what we spend our money and time on.
And so the biggest, you know, most, mostly
that is running well and it's doing,
you know, clearly there's always
bugs and we're always fixing things,
but there's a couple of things
that are really just kind of on
a technical level challenging.
And one of those things
is a search ranking.
And, and I've just, I spend a lot of
mental cycles on this of how to get good,
uh, search ranking without having to fall
back to the popularity scores or of,
of big silos and scraping
and this kind of stuff,
because I don't, number one,
I don't really trust some of their numbers
when, I mean, clearly it's like
Spotify, for instance, they are saying,
you know, they said that, uh,
Michelle Obama was their top podcast.
Okay.
Well, maybe, but then they opened it
up and made it not exclusive anymore,
which that makes me not
trust those numbers.
So if, if you're just scraping popularity
out of, out of silos and saying,
okay, well, these are, and I'm going to
wait my ranking in the index that same way.
I don't like that.
I don't think that's accurate.
I feel like there needs
to be something more
organic and something more decentralized.
I have not landed on anything.
Do you have any thoughts?
Well, I think you're going into it.
You're going into it with
the goal of putting,
putting the algorithm
together in such a way
to accurately represent what's going on.
And just having that goal is different
than, uh, somebody like a Spotify who,
again, their goal is to make money.
And I think that's, it's not a bad thing.
They have to make money.
They're, you know, they're a
company, but for, for podcast index,
it's a nonprofit, it's
an independent organization.
We're trying to solve this in a
different way, value for value.
And so I think, um, it's not necessarily
what the solution is right now.
It's that that's the goal.
And that's what we're trying.
And there's going to be, whatever we come
up with right now is going to change in a
month or six months or a year.
It's going to continue to iterate.
Um, but the goal is, is not going
to be convoluted with money.
Yeah.
That, because when, when people search
for things, so like podcast, uh,
let's just take out, you know,
plenty of apps to use our search.
Now when they search for things I
want, clearly there's going to be,
there's a need for some
sort of ranking or waiting or popularity
to inform, inform the rank, uh,
inform the results and the order.
And, and, but I don't, I don't want to
get caught into this trap of, oh, well,
these other, you
know, these other silos want, this is
how they've ranked it because I mean,
you can't, I just can't trust that.
You can't trust, you know, I can't
trust that, but, but I don't,
but then you don't want to
necessarily just, just discard it and
say, well, it's of no value whatsoever.
I'm trying to find this,
this middle ground between,
between trusting the algorithms and
having zero algorithm at all,
which also does not work.
Cause you gotta do, you
gotta do something.
Yeah.
Have you approached it
from the perspective of
like where Google started
off and, you know,
years ago, they came up
with this idea of page
rank where they would start scoring pages
based on somebody searches for this term.
And then they click on this page.
How long do they stay on that page?
Or do they come back and
search for something else?
And the longer they would stay on that
page, or if that would end their success,
then they knew that that
was a pretty strong result.
And so they'd start promoting it and
giving it higher and higher page rank.
It's evolved massively
since then, but that's,
that's the basis of kind
of where they started.
That's an interesting idea.
Yeah.
Giving people away.
So when they hit your index and they do
research and you give back these results,
then also giving them
a way to filter back.
Hey, okay.
This is the, the person clicked on
the third result that you showed me.
And then they ended up listening to an
episode or subscribing to that podcast.
So just let me know that.
I don't need to know anything
about who this person is,
but let me know that the third result
was the result that they
were actually looking for.
So then I can go to prioritize that
for this keyword going forward.
Yeah.
That makes a lot of sense.
Cause that, that's the, cause you
don't necessarily want, um, you know,
just a raw input where it
can be, I guess, gamed or misunderstood
where it's just like, okay, well,
I'm piping all the
clicks into this one score that you
need an extra, this sort of an extra,
like a arbitration layer there.
Uh, no, I like it.
Yeah.
I like that.
It's a good place to start.
And that the, you know, the other thing
now that we actually have some apps,
it's a little, it's a little easier
than it was at the beginning
because the beginning we
had zero inputs whatsoever.
I mean, it was just like,
there was nothing there.
And so, I mean, like now
that we have some apps
and we actually have some inputs, um, the
initial rate, uh, algorithms,
uh, worked out pretty good.
Just, just doing search misses.
It's like, okay, well,
somebody searched for this.
And so now let's rank up those things.
Uh, but I think it's time
to take the next step.
I appreciate that advice.
Yeah.
I mean, I really don't like the idea
of charts or especially charts from,
you know, like wall of garden silos
influencing search at all with search.
There's intense.
There's always a right answer.
Somebody is searching for something
because they're looking for something.
And even if I'm looking for a broad
category, like a type in baseball, I'm still
looking for, you know,
a specific baseball podcast that
is talking about little league
baseball or something,
even though I might've just taught
like typed in baseball, but there's
answers to these questions.
And the, the answer to
what are the most popular
podcasts in the world
is by saying, tell me
the most popular podcast in the world.
It's not by going to a search
and typing something in, right.
It's like, show me the chart.
So search, I feel like should
be a very different, you know,
like problem solution than just going
to the charts or using chart data
to influence our search results.
I don't, I don't think it's sort of
like search and discoverability.
They're really different things.
I don't know how y'all feel about that,
but like discoverability, you don't,
I think it's rare to discover
a podcast through a search.
I think search is to find
something you already
have an idea that you're
looking for, right?
Discoverability seems like
a different animal to me.
And I'm sure that we have some search gurus
who will be listening, who will jump in.
And we always encourage everybody
to come to podcastindex.social.
That's where a lot of these
things are fleshed out as,
and then of course the good
stuff moves off to the GitHub.
That's where I stop.
I'll check, I'll check
in once, once every,
like maybe every three
days, see what Daniel J.
Lewis has posted.
Yeah.
It's always fun to read.
He's got interesting ideas.
So to bring it back to the
podcasting 2.0, Dave, you're,
we have the namespace phase one
locking down November
15th, if I'm correct.
Yeah.
And I think, I don't know
how Tom and Kevin feel,
but I feel like it's pretty
much come into clarity now.
I think we have a pretty good, pretty
good finish line in front of us.
Yeah.
I think we're super excited.
We can't wait for the 15th because
I mean, at the 15th we're locked.
We have a spec, like everyone get
your apps together, get on board.
Start implementing this
stuff, get everyone excited,
get your audience members excited
about these new things.
Like, Hey, here's my podcast now.
And it does not just
my podcast also has my
picture and the picture of
the guests that was on there.
So what are the, what are
the tags we are that are,
are good to go for phase one, the
transcript, the locked
funding chapters, soundbite.
And then the one that we're
working on right now is person.
Ah, yes.
Right.
And could, could someone explain
to me the use case of soundbite?
Because I've honestly, I've kind
of missed that conversation.
Sure.
I mean, I think about soundbite as, I
mean, you remember what is eighties,
nineties, you drive into a new
town and you don't know any
of the radio stations
and you hit that scan
button on your FM radio.
Yeah.
You're like, show me all the
cool stations in this town.
You had FM, huh?
Wow.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, I mean, you could,
that's one use case.
You could use it like that.
You could say, um, Hey, I'm looking for a
new sports podcast and now we go ahead,
we play all these 30, 45, you know,
minute and a half soundbites from,
from anybody who's pushing soundbites out.
So this is a, um, so the way I just
want to understand how to use it.
So I use it by saying,
here's a clip and I guess,
I guess you can have more than one,
but here's, here's a clip from this show.
And that just goes as an
additional tag as if it were, um,
that that's for discoverability.
So someone can just preview and
listen to something from the show.
And I've determined what that is.
Is that correct?
Right.
So you, as the creator, you say, Hey,
this episode's two hours long
at 23 minutes and 30 seconds.
Here's a 45 second soundbite
that really fun and interesting.
So if you want to kind of get a flavor for
the show, just listen to this 45 seconds.
And then after that,
you can decide if you want to subscribe
or listen to the whole thing or whatever.
And there's another later on.
And so how does that function?
Do I have to clip an actual soundbite
or is it a piece from the file?
What is the, I have not followed
the tag, so I'm not sure.
Piece from the file.
Yeah.
It's a piece from the file.
It's not just time.
It's just time stamp and a duration.
That's beautiful.
At 45 seconds, play a 30 second clip.
And that's the soundbite that, you know,
we want to be able to
highlight for that episode.
I like that.
Whose idea was that?
That's Kevin.
Yeah.
Well, it came from Buzzsprout.
We've been letting people create
soundbites for their podcasts for years,
but then we had nothing to do.
Like we couldn't stick them in the RSS
feed because no apps were doing it.
And right.
Right.
If we said everyone should be doing this.
So we just created a little
video files and we're like,
share them on your Twitter, share
them on your Facebook, whatever
you want to do with it.
Now that we have it, we're like, oh my
gosh, this is, this makes perfect sense.
This is where it should
have been all along.
Yeah.
Well, that, that makes sense.
We're, uh, you know, I don't know if
y'all saw what I started putting in,
um, soundbite support in, uh, the
index aggregators, uh, last night.
And, um, what, you know, I mean,
one of the, as soon as it's done,
one of the first, one
of my first use cases for
the index is going to
be just a new API endpoint where it's just
says recent soundbites or
soundbites by category.
And it just basically just
be a, you know, a stream of,
of the latest soundbites
that are discovered.
Um, I think that'll be, that's
basically like your scan button,
but you got to have some
buffering and stuff, don't you?
How, how the hell does that work?
Does, can you do an HTTP
request straight into
the file at a certain point
or how does that work?
Yeah, you can cause a bite range request.
So you can just say the file I want and
start at this bite range or whatever.
It should, it should work,
you know, quote unquote.
And how do I author that?
Is there, and are there any
tools out there to do that?
Well, I guess, I got to just move
my whole feed over to buzzsprout.
What the hell, man?
It's like, I just need to,
you want to take my traffic?
I'll, I'll do it for 12 bucks a month.
I think that's, that's a good deal for me.
Yeah.
It's only, it's only a terabyte
and a half of traffic.
It's not a big deal.
I bet, I bet someone at buzzsprout
saw me sign up to like, oh crap.
Oh no.
We can't have that guy
bringing his stuff over here.
No, no.
He said, Adam just signed up.
I upgraded him to free.
I was like, oh my gosh, we're
going to lose it on this one.
Well, well, Hey man, Steve jobs did
it for me the first time around.
So you're in good company, you know,
he upgraded my Mac drive to let me,
to let me do all this stuff.
So, um, you know, Dave and I talked
about this before we started the show,
um, because we wanted to, uh, show you guys
some stuff that we've been working on.
And we think that it's probably, uh,
in the tradition of podcast
index to do it publicly
and, and, and talk to you a little
bit about what we're doing.
Um, you know, when we started the, we had,
it's, it's always been on the website.
We have two main missions.
One preserve podcasting as
a platform for free speech.
And I think, I think we're
well on our way to doing that.
We have the index filled up.
We've got people contributing,
keeping, uh, and by the way,
we'll be thanking people who,
uh, who donated to sponsor a machine.
We'll be thanking you on the next episode.
Um, we, so, you know, it is to a
degree self-sustaining, you know,
Dave's not getting paid, you know,
I'm not getting paid, but that's
not the point it's, it's running.
And I think we are, you know,
seeing the adoption and people
adding us now as an option,
uh, for search and, uh, into their apps
and some, some big ones too, you know,
like podcast addict, which is really nice.
And seeing all this plethora of new apps
coming online with new experiences.
I think we, I think we are
well on our way to achieving
that goal and being able to maintain it.
Second part of the mission, uh,
which Dave and I were thinking
about from day one was retooling
podcasting as a platform of value.
And we, and you guys are interesting,
uh, because of your overall philosophy,
which falls very much in line with ours,
which, uh, if I could sum it up is, uh,
the days of free have to end.
And I believe the podcast audiences
are well primed and ready, uh,
to look at a different
value model than they've
previously been using.
When I say value model, uh, the,
the one that is most known that
people default to is advertising.
Um, my personal view cut down
real short is advertising
is censorship because it always
leads to censorship one way or the
other, probably self-censorship.
Um, and we have seen
that the value for value
model as deployed on no agenda as deployed
on podcast index, which is really
whatever you're getting out of this,
put something back in.
And we asked for your time,
your talent, or your treasure.
And a lot of people are
very happy to when it's
open-ended and they can
determine the value
of how much they want to give back,
it works a hell of a lot better than
saying tip us five bucks a month.
And, uh, and why, I don't
know, but it's true.
And, uh, we saw Patreon rise and Patreon
has a lot of, a lot of pros, uh, uh,
versus the
cons, you know, it, it, it, it allows
people to, uh, support media property,
support their, uh, their clubs,
their groups, their tribes,
the podcast that they
center around, um, has
a lot of issues, it's, uh, clearly, uh,
you can be de-platformed from it, um,
and maybe not even de-platformed
by a Patreon alone,
but down the line at the
credit card processing.
Um, there's just a lot
of different issues.
So what I do know, and
actually I'm going to, if,
are you guys able to access email, Tom
and, uh, and Kevin, I'm sending you an
email right now with little presentation.
Um, and Dave, you have it in front of you.
Yeah, I go.
So the second part of our mission,
which we haven't really
spoken about that publicly
is why are we doing this?
You know, what is for, for part two for
retooling podcasting as a platform, uh,
uh, value, but we, we really need to
free podcasting from corporate control.
And this is another thing that
I think Kevin and Tom, you,
you both identify this as
being a very big issue.
So how we're going to do that is we have
to continue to have decentralized content.
We have to integrate it
with decentralized money.
And I say decentralized
money because we know that
platform for free speech is very difficult
when you're using third
parties and payment processors
and all these different places where
you can just get removed from.
So we're thinking a step ahead, um,
which is, is always going to be,
is always going to take
an adoption process.
And what we're doing is we're building a
self-sustaining ecosystem for podcasting.
Do you guys have this,
uh, this PDF that I sent?
Yeah, I've got it.
So if you look at the second slide, and
I'll post this on the podcast index.social.
So this is, uh, the model that Dave and
I looked at from the very beginning,
um, that there are, and these are
interactive advertising bureau numbers.
So this is just us numbers.
There's a hundred million
us podcast listeners
who on average listen one hour per day.
And as some listen to hell of a lot
more, some listen less, but on average,
you have a hundred million hours
of content being consumed per day.
Based on my experience over a decade
with no agenda show, MoFax, uh,
with podcast index, uh,
looking at Patreon,
I believe we can convert at least 1% of
those 100 million listening hours per day.
So 100 million people,
we should be able to get 1 million
people to want to pledge to a
podcast instead of, uh, not pay for
it or go through any other system.
So I'm thinking more
model where, you know,
this show is worth something
to me and I'm just
pegging that to make it
simple at $1 an hour.
So if in, and I know that if
I ask my listeners and I say,
what is the show worth to you, they'll
probably set it a lot higher
than a, than a dollar per hour,
but it's a, it's a fair price.
And I think everybody can, can find
themselves in that kind of range.
So now you're talking about a
potential daily flow of $1 million.
And this is a stream of
value that we have been
able to capture into a
self-sustaining system.
And it's, it's a mind bender.
So if you're already on slide three and
four, you're probably going, what the hell?
Um, and Dave jump in anytime here.
So I'm going to explain what
the, the, the history of what,
what happened in the background
as we were building the index,
I dove in deep into, uh,
digital money and how it would work
and how we could basically
stream that at the same time.
Someone is streaming MP3
bits, ones and zeros.
I thought it would be
entertaining and interesting
to see if we could stream
value, some monetary
value back to the creator and
back to the app you're using.
And anyone else who was in the chain of
value that brought this program to you.
And there's a new protocol that
is a part of the, well, it's a,
it's a Bitcoin off chain
protocol called lightning.
Uh, this is developed by lightning labs.
That is the company that
Jack Dorsey funded.
Uh, and, and this is really, I
think it's been around since 2018.
It's, uh, it is on main net.
So it's actually working.
It's, uh, it's functional and there's one,
let me stop at the stop, Adam real quick.
Just ask Kevin and Tom.
I mean, how familiar are you guys with
how Bitcoin and this kind of stuff works?
Are y'all, what's your skill level there?
Uh, mine is very high level.
I mean, I've bought some Bitcoins.
I've played around with a few different
digital currencies a little bit,
but super high level,
never dug into the development side or how
it all gets connected and just around.
Yeah.
Same here.
Okay.
All right.
Just checking.
So you've, you've at least had a wallet at
one point and you've had Bitcoin in it or
some kind of digital currency.
Correct.
What's interesting about
the lightning protocol
is it allows you to stream micro payments.
So thousands of a Satoshi,
so very, very small amounts.
And you can stream it directly
without creating an invoice.
As long as you have someone's public
key, you can send it in real time.
And, uh, I was looking at this.
I set up a full Bitcoin, Bitcoin node, uh,
Dave and I was doing a
lot more in the beginning
because Dave was focusing on, uh, on keeping
the databases and everything running.
And, you know, once we kind
of were able to really
dive in and understand what's happening,
um, we met these guys who also
showed up on no agenda social, uh,
on podcast index.social.
And that's the guys from Sphinx chat.
And we, and so what they have, and I, and
I always kind of knew this would happen.
They kind of have a peanut butter and
we're sticking our chocolate into it.
They've created chat app that
is very much like WeChat.
Are you familiar with
WeChat, Kevin and Tom?
So, you know, WeChat
basically does everything.
You can pay your bills.
You can do all kinds of stuff with it.
Um, and super app is what they call it.
Super app.
Yeah.
And everything costs a
little bit of money.
So, uh, even sending a message to someone
costs one, one hundredths of a penny,
I think is what the lowest denominator is.
Um, and they integrated,
uh, with our help,
but it was quite easy
because there's so much
available on the GitHub, et cetera,
that, you know, the roadmap is there.
They integrated podcasting into their app.
And after we discussed the pledge
idea, they now have a working, uh,
proof of concept where
you get the app, you go to the
podcast you want to listen to.
And the minute you hit play every minute,
a little bit of money is
streaming off and that
money is streamed off
to the podcaster, uh,
with an automatic split to the
podcast app they're using.
And we've just set that at 1%.
We thought that would be fair
to start off with the market.
We'll have to tell us
what's right or wrong.
Podcast index receives 1%,
um, keep everything running.
And the podcaster can then determine
what other money they need to split up.
So if they have a cohost or if
they have a hosting company,
or if they have promoters, or if they
have an investor or anybody, they
can personally go in, uh, say, okay,
I want 50% of what I get
to go to this person, 10% to that
person, 10% to this service.
And, uh, and it, and the minute someone
is using that podcast app, which is chat.
And it's also a digital wallet.
They are actually paying
directly from their wallet
to all those other people in real time,
uh, at the value they determine.
Does that make sense?
That makes sense.
That sounds like the, that sounds
like a magical future though.
Well, the thing is wrapping
my head around this is huge.
Yeah.
Well, so, so to jump in
real quick, the, so that,
the idea here is first of all, none, none
of this is proprietary.
None of this depends on
the index to function.
Anybody can, as long as you have
a public, uh, lightning node, uh,
that can accept key
send, you can drop, um, and the way, the
way, the way this will ultimately be,
you know, come to fruition is in an open
way is there will be tag that will,
that will be put into, they'll
be put into the, into the namespace,
uh, that will define where the, these,
these addresses and what
the split percentages are.
So if I'm a podcaster and
I have a, a lightning,
a Bitcoin lightning node
that can accept key
send payments, I'll take my, my nodes ID
and I will just construct the XML, uh,
for this we're calling it the
value block or the value tag.
You can drop it into
your XML feed and any,
any podcast app that is
aware of how to send
key send payments can
read that and immediately
know where to begin streaming payments.
Now the, so, so it's not dependent
on us, the, the end, the, we will,
we have already built
support for it in a way to be able
to make this a little bit easier.
And so anything that
comes through us, we, uh,
we put a 1% split in there just to help us
cover our cost and to
help support the index.
Uh, but this is where hosting
plays, plays the role.
And I think you can see that
in the, in the PDF is, um,
what we envision is that hosting
companies will be, will be payment
hubs essentially that, that,
because one thing that this, one
thing that's necessary here is to allow
your, allow podcasters to have a, uh,
a lightning node that can accept payments.
And that in order for, uh, one of the
roles for, for a hosting company,
it says you're already
providing the, um, the,
the feed services and the tools is
you could also provide, uh, lightning
nodes, uh, and spin those up.
And then you take a, and then you just,
you get a percentage, one, two, 5%,
whatever you negotiate
with your customers.
And so as the streaming payments
are coming through, um,
there's a percentage coming off
to this getting peeled off to the
hoster and that, you know, that could,
that could cut, that could
help that could cover costs.
That could be pure, you know,
that could be a profit, whatever,
however that plays out
with your internal business.
And let me, let me say a little
bit more about this hub.
Um, so what I think will happen, and by the
way, all the code for this is available.
There's a GitHub, GitHub, um, there's
a code that can be dropped into,
uh, existing pot.
I mean, I say it, here's
my non-developer voice.
You can drop that code right into your
app and that shit will work overnight.
Okay.
So we know the reality of that, but
there, there's code to make simple, um,
simple podcast apps that don't
need to receive key send.
They can just send, but the hub, because
everything happens on blockchain,
the hubs become super
interesting for community-based features.
So, uh, in the demo, we'll show you guys
and, um, and we're going to, you know,
get as many people in as
possible starting next week.
It depends on the Sphinx chat guys, cause
you know, there it's their hub, their,
uh, nodes, et cetera, they're
spinning up and we have a whole
claim your podcaster
wallet process set up.
The hub, uh, has chat
features, relay features, uh,
all these community-based features that
when you see the app, they
actually have a timeline.
And as the podcast is running
very much like YouTube, uh,
you can chat along with
people at the same time.
And that is going to be
on the podcaster hub,
but obviously because
it's blockchain that can
be propagated to all hubs, which is,
I think very exciting because
these are the interactive
features that we've been looking for.
Um, you can also do, uh,
what we're calling a boost.
So if you just, if you're
listening and you hear
something really cool and you just want
to hit it with a little boost,
you get a whole animation and
100 Satoshis goes to the, goes
down the chain through all of the splits.
Um, I don't know if they've
implemented it yet,
but the idea is when you come back in,
just like on YouTube and
you play the show again,
you can see the replay of the chat and
you can add to that and
participate in, uh, in, you know,
kind of that virtual comment
slash chat timeline that is just being
added to with every person that comes in.
I mean, all of these features are
all pretty much functional today,
including the ability
to set how much value we have.
I think max is a hundred Satoshis now,
but you can set it to one per
minute or whatever you want.
Um, and that should be able
to go higher, obviously, uh,
seeing as that 12,000 Satoshis is now $1.
So you see, there's a,
there's a lot of things that are
going to take people getting used to.
Um, there's no doubt that
there's an onboarding
process for people to
even have Bitcoin and
understand how to get it
from point A to point B.
There's a ton of very well-funded
companies who are doing that.
Uh, but we feel this hub
role, which is the last page,
that that is something that you guys
could do and other hosting
companies as well.
And, and just to point out, to reiterate
what Dave said, just like podcast index.
All of this, you don't need us to do this.
Uh, we'd love to be included
in, in everybody's, uh,
ecosystem because we have a lot, you know,
set up and good to go, but it's, you know,
anybody can set up an index and do this.
But, uh, the, uh, the, this to me is
turbo charging podcasting with a defined,
uh, market defined value stream.
The same PR works, you know, Hey, uh,
I'd be willing to give you money, Mr.
Podcaster.
If I can use this app with your podcast,
the onboarding for that is very simple.
We've got that licked and hopefully
it will feed upon itself.
Um, but what we'll need is companies that
want to provide these extra services,
uh, which are
all, you know, established, uh, type
of server services that are, you know,
I don't know exactly
what, what it all entails, but I have,
I have a node running at my house.
So, you know, if I can do something,
then you guys may be able to do
many more of those some things.
Um, what, what would the experience
look like for the listener?
So the listener would need to
have a lightning node as well.
No, the, the, you'd have to
have some type of currency.
Yeah.
So you have a, an app and
that app will basically
just have a wallet strapped onto it.
And there's code for that
available already, um,
which can be done in a
web app, Android or iOS.
And once you have that set up,
then essentially once you get the
value block from the RSS feed
or from the index, you can immediately
start participating in this and, uh,
your player that you just hit
play and it all goes, uh,
you will have to configure
my player to connect to
that as, to be able to pull
as, as an app developer.
So let's take a pod friend as an example,
pod friend would function
exactly the way it does
today, um, only there
would be an additional
configuration where you
go into your wallet
so you can receive money, put
money in there and then, uh,
the equivalent of subscribe to
a podcast and it'll just work.
If there's no money in your
wallet, it'll still work.
This is a pledge.
It's not a, it's not a, a pay to play.
It's actually the opposite.
It's play to pay.
So you've got, you've got, um, you
know, even, yeah, I mean, even if the,
uh, podcaster
does not have a wallet set up, it'll still
function as, as regular, but we may,
or a pod friend who would have
an incentive to say, Hey, uh,
you could be paying this podcaster and
click here to make that happen.
Uh, because that app pod
friend in this case would
get a 1% of the value stream for someone
who's using their app to
listen to the podcast.
Yeah, there's a, there's a thing we've
been talking about since the beginning.
And I'll try to clarify
one thing is one of the
things we've been talking about from the
beginning is that app developers
have been left out of the podcast,
podcast ecosystem in
a big way since the beginning.
And, you know, those guys are, uh, you
know, you got hosting companies that,
that can make
an, you know, y'all can make enough money
to, uh, to, to survive and pay y'all's
bills, uh, podcasters, uh, may not be me.
I'm making a fortune, but those
guys are making, you know,
making some good money too.
But the podcast app
developers really are let
have been left to sell their stuff for in
app purchases or 99 cents
on an app store for years.
And so like one of the,
so to clarify the way that that
works and the way this gets them
into the flow of so that they can
make a living also is that, um, the,
um, essentially will
be the same as they are now, but they
become, they become a, a wallet.
So basically they are a, um,
they just strap on a Bitcoin
wallet to their smart wallet.
Yeah.
A lightning, they put a
lightning wallet function
into their app so that
now I can transfer some
Bitcoin over to my podcast app, uh,
to my podcast app from cat
from cash app or PayPal
or wherever I'm getting my Bitcoin from.
I send some Bitcoin over
to my podcast player.
And now, um, then now I see that this
favorite podcast that I'm listening to,
uh, supports the value block and it
shows, uh, a lightning payment address.
And I just say, oh yeah, I'll give
them, you know, a dollar an hour, uh,
that I'll listen to it.
And it just boom, boom, boom.
It just starts happening
in the background.
So basically the, that's, that's
the idea is that podcast players,
podcast apps become wallets.
We've been working with, uh, uh, Paul
and Evan from Sphinx chat and you'll,
you'll see Paul show up on a
podcast index on social for sure.
Um, and there, the, the
vibe in the Bitcoin
development community is very
analogous to podcasting.
And I'll sum it up with
something Paul said to us.
He said, there should be no
billionaires coming out of this.
Everybody should be able to make
money fair, compete on features,
compete on price, compete
on speed, whatever it is.
Uh, if, if anyone walks out a billionaire
because they've siloed something,
then we, we fucked it up.
We did something wrong.
Uh, what I love about it is all the code
is made available and it's updated.
It's fresh.
Uh, they cannot, um, they
cannot single-handedly do this.
We can't single-handedly do this.
We've got to drive adoption and, uh,
getting this value block into
the next phase of the namespace.
Uh, but just developing with it now,
uh, at a point where I think we're all,
we've got a lot of excitement, a lot of
momentum where people are now seeing, Hey,
we've got these great
features, but you know, if you use
my tool, you got tags over here.
If you use that tool,
you got tags over there.
Now, all of a sudden we have a reason
to expand the ecosystem and have, uh,
these podcaster hubs,
which will allow for these, um,
these community features to not
only happen in a way that is
completely anonymous, completely secure,
uh, it's cryptographically insured to,
you know, for trust also provides
built-in spam protection because
you could make things very expensive for
somebody trying to spam.
If you're just charging little amounts,
you know, that's, that's always, if, if,
if, uh, email cost you one cent,
there would be no spammers anymore.
So that's kind of built into the protocol.
Tom, I hear you tapping
away on your keyboard.
Are you sending a message to have
me arrested or what are you doing?
I'm Googling some of this stuff.
I have not, I've not heard a lot of this.
So let me, uh, go ahead, Tom, Kevin,
I was just saying that I
was looking at different
lightning nodes and what it
takes to integrate with one.
Cause as the host side, we
would be, we're not a player.
And so we would be the
integration on our side
would be to make sure
that we could provide
that in the RSS feed so that the money
can get routed, uh, appropriately.
Um, as a, as a hoster.
Yeah.
So, uh, hosting a full node for,
uh, for receiving, uh, lightning.
And then there's these, uh,
additional bits that, uh,
Sphinx chat has made available.
And that's, uh, the chat that's the, they
have a meme server for, uh, you know, GIFs
and, and images, et cetera.
And, and again, all of this
rides on the blockchain
is really phenomenal
because, you know, you can,
you can join in just with
your, with your public key.
I mean, it is, it is very, very exciting.
So all of that stuff, all those
services are built within the, uh,
the LND node, which is the lightning node.
And, you know, there's a, uh, there's a,
an obvious cost, uh, um, per month to,
to host that, uh, which could be something
that you guys could provide in that,
in that manner.
Um, but I, I think, you know, I'll,
I'll leave that up to you
because obviously any podcaster
could set up their own node.
I mean, I have one at home and I could
do my own node services, but that's me.
And I also do my own RSS feed.
So I'm not your typical guy.
Yeah.
I think the, the thing to, uh,
light lightning, if you've never,
if you're only partially for
me with Bitcoin, then lightning is
going to make your head explode.
I mean, I'll just go ahead and say that.
I mean, it's not some, it is once
somebody can explains it to you,
it makes perfect sense.
It's not, it's not magic and it's
not a mystery, but it's just,
it really is a head twister
when you first sort of get, uh, get
familiar with it because it allows, uh,
Bitcoin, uh, so, well, the problem
with Bitcoin now is that the
transaction time is so long
and the fees are so expensive.
So, I mean, you can take, you know, uh,
the fees are large if you
want something less than
a six hour confirmation
time to send Bitcoin from
one wallet to another
lightning solves that
by making all the transactions off chain.
So that the transactions, um,
get sent in real time and small amounts
for no fee or zero or very little fee.
And then the trend and then those, all
those transactions are batched together,
uh, later
and then brought back on chain and at
one time so that you have, it's a mind,
it's a, it's a, it's a mind F.
I mean, it's impossible
to explain in words and,
and honestly for the podcaster and for
the listener, it shouldn't be difficult.
All it is, is put money
in the top, press play.
That's it.
And then enjoy all the features
that come along with that.
Yeah.
So what we're trying to do is just put the
plumbing together for it to make this,
to make it all flow because
the, and, and I say plumbing,
I mean like the plumbing in
the decentralized plumbing
that goes through all of RSS and that
kind of thing, because the, the,
the way that this will get adoption is
when people, uh, begin to have, you know,
have nodes available to
them and that kind of
thing, which is not hard.
I mean, I have a node, uh, Adam's
running his node, uh, Sphinx,
the Sphinx chat guys,
they spin up nodes for you.
Uh, it's there's, these services
are out there, but it is very new.
And so this is a long-term
vision that we have.
But when I say long-term, I mean, I,
I think that this, I'm not, this,
I'm not talking five years long-term.
I mean, I'm talking about,
you know, six months.
Well, I mean, this, and this other transactions
would take place like that, right?
Decentralized and yeah.
Right.
Well, so, um, and we're going
to get you guys, uh, uh,
access to the app so you can, so you
can see it in action.
Uh, we have, uh, we have like
two or three podcasts that, uh,
that we've enabled this way.
And, you know, the whole process is
really, you look at this and you're like,
this is, this is a whole
new podcasting app.
And my hope has always been that,
you know, with these two worlds,
we have hundreds, if
not thousands of wallets.
Everyone's got a wallet and you
can use it as a point of sale.
You know, it's got a
little, Oh, I can use it.
Like I'm charging people money.
And then, you know, it was like
a little credit card thing,
or you can click on a marketplace.
So you can go buy server space or some
wires or solder, whatever this is.
It's not a lot of things.
It's not like an Amazon.
You can also be a cashier
Bitcoin in for gift cards,
which you can then use on Amazon, but
wait until these guys see
the podcasting opportunity.
They're going to turn their
wallets into podcast apps.
And I think that we have this interesting,
I hope to see some cross
collaboration too.
I think we have an
interesting mix of podcast
app developers and wallet
developers, and we
can come together and we can
create some kick ass stuff.
And it doesn't have to be,
this is, you know, this,
another beauty of this thing is it does
not in any way exclude traditional
advertising based funding.
No.
I mean, you can continue to have
ads and do whatever you want to,
but then you also drop
this thing into your feed
and that enables a lightning
aware podcast app apps begin to, to
send you money on a, on a
stream streaming basis.
And that's an extra
source of income that can
give you protection from
possibly being de-platformed.
Can you guys help me understand the difference
between a, like a node and a wallet?
Yeah.
The node is the backend,
just to make it simple.
So the wallet holds your keys,
has all the logic in it.
But your wallet is on your phone.
Typically it's not going
to be online 24 seven.
So you need what they call a watchtower.
So there's a little
process running in, uh,
on the server that is making
sure you're receiving,
you know, whatever, whatever needs to be
done so that when you reconnect your,
your wallet, uh, you can then, um, uh,
see how much money you've received,
but you can also make payments
and do other things.
Uh, so the note is, am I
saying that right, Dave?
The note is basically you're,
you're always on presence.
Yeah.
The, yeah, the note is,
is what is communicating.
The lightning note is
what's communicating with
the Bitcoin client at
all times in order to
manage, uh, connections
between the lightning
network and the Bitcoin
network and open and
close channels and do
all this kind of stuff.
And the wallet is just sort of, it's
almost a virtual construct on top of that,
just so that
you can see your money and trend and make
transactions and that kind of thing.
And, and, and use the node
for chat and other things.
Yeah.
The, the lightning L and D is the
main, is the main implementation.
Uh, there's, there's a couple
of others see lightning,
but I think L and D may be the
only one that supports
key center right now.
Uh, does everybody who
wants to be able to send
currency through lightning need their own
node or can you share nodes?
No, there's actually, um,
there's a lot of, uh,
node providers or as they call lightning
service providers and breeze B R E E Z E
seems to be leading the pack right now.
And they have a code on
GitHub and they have pretty
much a full lightning node running on
the wallet and I believe
they have a watchtower
in the background that
they provide to people.
So they have, you know, it's
kind of like a split service,
but you hold your keys in your wallet.
Um, and they have enabled
key send payments from that.
So you really only need,
you really just need whatever
infrastructure they're providing,
um, to, to send your, your
payments to any receiving node.
The receiving node really needs to be on
all the time with your breeze wallet.
You reconnect, it's re-syncing,
it re-syncs real fast.
It's, it's a, a neutrino, um, uh, wallet.
So it's, it, as Dave was
explaining, it, it, it,
it grabs a much smaller
slice of the blockchain
to make sure it has payment confirmation.
Um, but it can't receive, uh, can't do
key send receive unless it's online.
So that's just basically not functional.
So in order to receive, you need the,
the node, the full node to send,
it can be just
a, a temporary client that has enough
knowledge to, to make those payments,
uh, when connected.
Yeah.
It's an interesting, like, you know,
what we've been working with
the Sphinx guys with, uh,
they, they, they, they provide
nodes and they also provide,
and they also had the Sphinx app.
And so we, it was, it was
a good combination because
they could provide both in order for
us to do this, like proof of concept.
Uh, let's see if this thing
even works type of deal.
And, uh, cause they had an app that they,
they essentially turned
their Sphinx, excuse
me, their lightning wallet app into a
podcast app in the course of about a month.
Um, and so that, that kind of
tells you what, what that entails.
I mean, it tells you what
kind of how I'm not,
I don't want to use the
word simple because
it is not simple, but what
I'm trying to say is like,
it tells you that it's not, there's
a good integration there
that exists already.
Uh, now the, the node hosting is, uh,
something that it's just going to be,
it's going to be a learning curve.
And I think the Sphinx guys will
be happy to lend, uh, Derek.
Yeah.
Paul, Paul is going to be on, uh, on
the Mastodon server as much as he can.
And, uh, you know, we'll
have pointers and all
kinds of stuff for
anybody who's interested.
Um, Evan is one of their developers.
I may, I don't know if he'll have time,
but he'll certainly be available.
And what we'd like to do is right
after we're done here, Kevin and Tom,
Tom, we'd like to get you, uh, uh,
suited up on the app and, and, uh,
walk through it with us.
So you have a little better idea and, uh,
then you can explain to
the next guy how it works.
Yeah.
So, I mean, I think I have my
head wrapped around the vision,
the implementation part
is still a little fuzzy, but I'll
get clear, but the vision, right?
Like I should be able to open up
my podcast app player of choice.
So let's say it's, it's pod friend
and I've got this digital currency,
lightning, something or other.
It's basically Bitcoin.
Okay.
And I say, Hey, I want to pay $10 a
month to my favorite podcasters, right?
So the first of every month, go ahead and
drop 10 bucks in my, my pod friend wallet.
And configure pod friend that
says, Hey, for the first,
I got $10 a month coming in here.
So, and I want to do a
dollar a minute for the
first 600 minutes of podcasts I listened
to in pod friend every month, dish
that out to my favorite podcast.
And that's it.
Exactly.
That's it.
And then while you're doing that, you're,
you're supporting
everybody all the way down
the chain that you're supporting
the app you're using pod friend,
you're supporting the index
and, uh, anything else that the podcaster,
uh, and this is kind of as a podcaster,
I really like this feature
that automatically half of it
can go to my co-host and it goes straight
to my co-host wallet.
You know, we don't have to have any
conversation about it after that, uh,
10% can go to my investors who, who
supported me and getting my gear, et cetera.
And that is, is all control.
That's all completely
transparent, uh, in two ways.
One is you don't, you
don't see it happening,
but you do get all the receipts for it.
Uh, but you can see it just, it all
goes in one fell swoop all the way.
And that it's amazing.
We have, we have that
part actually working.
It's like also transparent, right?
If I'm understanding is because you could
always view the source of the RSS feed and
there's that value right there telling
you how it's being distributed.
That's exactly right.
And that's why we, we put, uh, uh, if
you, if you go through the index to get,
um, when we start exposing the value
block, uh, stuff that we aggregate,
if we expose it through
the API, we'll have our
split in there at 1%.
Uh, and that's, uh, for, you know,
for the same thing, transparency,
we're just asking for a,
essentially a donation.
And that would be something that, uh,
you know, that a hoster could do.
You could say, well, here's,
you know, here's your feed.
You're producing the feed
and then you have a node.
Buzzsprout has a, has a lightning node
that's sitting there and you say, okay,
well, you know, you can, uh, here's your,
we produce your feed and we're going
to add our 1% to your value block.
And so we get a, we get a piece
of, of a 1% of that as well.
And, uh, maybe, you know, it
can, it's a sliding scale.
I mean, there's a market for it.
So who knows what those prices are
supposed to be right now, but the other,
the other thing, um, but it's like
you said, yes, it's all transparent.
It's right there in the XML feed.
You can just see, you can see it all.
You see where the money's going.
The, the other thing though, this not to
complicate things, but it's a little,
um, you
thinking, thinking beyond the digital currency
part of it is that in the, one of the
reasons why Adam had the idea of
doing it on a minute by minute basis,
instead of just as, as lump sums
is because this gives you insight
into what's happening during the playing
of your app, excuse me, playing
of your, of your episode.
I mean, if, if all of a sudden you start,
you start seeing payments
drop off at a certain
point in your episode, and
of course it's Bitcoin.
So it's all anonymous, anonymous anyway,
there's no user exposure, but I mean,
it can give you
insight into, well, maybe that's not
a very good part of your episode.
So like, or if, if people begin to
give you boost payments, you know,
they're like, Oh, bing, bing, bing,
you know, this, this was great.
Well, maybe you want to, that
informs you in a different way.
Oh, well that they like that segment.
So, I mean, it has more than
just a, a, a funding function.
It's also a very valuable information
tool when you're having, uh,
sequenced payments coming
in on a minute by minute basis.
And, and I'll, I will mention that in
all this testing and we've had the,
the money at a very low level.
So I'm getting, you know, what is a one
Satoshi is one, one hundredth of a penny.
I think, um, just to
see that streaming in,
I'm looking at this log and like in an app
on my phone, like, Oh, boom, boom, boom.
And so I know that
someone's listening now,
of course it's either
Dave or Evan or Paul and
they're developing and they're
testing, but it's exciting.
It doesn't matter how, how
much it is like, Oh my God.
So I can actually see listeners coming in.
It's, it's, it's an incredible experience.
Yeah.
And you're not having to rely on,
I be certified download stats
and all this kind of stuff.
None of that first impressions.
That's a mind bender, man.
I may have said that once or twice myself.
Yeah.
It took me quite a while
to that's, I've been,
I've been harping on this for a while.
I say digital money and I
don't care if it's Bitcoin
or a fed now digital dollar or a digital
Euro, you got to think
differently about it.
And you can, especially this.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
There's no, I mean, there
has to be a way, right.
For an open ecosystem, like
a, what am I calling like a,
like a protocol instead of a platform
being able to distribute money because we
want to be able to support our podcasters.
I'm, I'm happy to give, you know, Netflix
my $12 a month, but how do I give my,
you know, 10 or 15 favorite podcasters?
Well, this, this is the
example that I like the
most because what we're seeing now after
everyone being home a
lot for Corona, uh, Ms.
Rona paying her visit is, you know, you're
paying, uh, you know, 15 bucks for
Netflix, uh, 15 bucks for Hulu.
You got your Amazon purchases.
And of course you really only use
a few from each of these silos.
Whereas the way we look at it is you,
you determine what you want to
listen to and you route right
around or right through those
silos, however, people are, uh,
and whatever app people are
listening in and you determine
where your money goes.
There should be no reason.
And by the way, Spotify
can easily put this into
the system if they're
interested in it easily.
I said, hold for laughter.
I don't know.
No, but I mean, I'm just saying
that it's, it's that open.
Oh yeah.
I mean, we would all love that.
Right.
I don't know that.
I don't know.
I feel very optimistic.
Well, I think the bottom
line is it doesn't matter.
You know, I'm, I'm, I'm not
making money off of Spotify.
Um, it comes directly from the
producers who produce the show.
Um, people figured out Patreon.
So I, I really don't have any doubt that
if people like the concept, which is,
uh, pledging,
here's what I'm going to
pay for my listening.
And instead of, uh, a hundred
dollars at the end of the month,
if we let the silos grow, I'll
have $30 at the end of the month.
And that's what I spend on my podcast.
And oh, by the way, if I run out, I can
just feel bad about it and not care,
um, or I can top it up.
It doesn't matter.
It won't stop your listening experience.
Yeah.
There's a, here's the thing is that
Spotify and, and Apple podcasts,
these are not great
podcasting apps anyway.
No, they're not.
The reality is, is once
you become a podcast fan,
you're probably going
to find something else.
Yeah.
Right.
And especially if you get podcasters who
start talking about this, like, Hey,
this show isn't free from me to produce.
There's this way that you can support
me and other podcasts you love,
and it's available in these apps
and they're excellent apps.
So if you're discovering this show here
or here that doesn't support that,
I would encourage you to check this out.
Like if we can start getting
that message out, uh, yeah,
you absolutely don't need a Spotify
to adopt something like this
because again, podcast,
podcast fans will find dedicated apps.
Well, I, I can't wait to start
pushing this on my shows because I,
I think people will give it a shot.
And again, we only need 1%.
You get 1%, then all of
a sudden we've got the
pump is primed and stuff is moving through
and who knows who will
come in with another idea.
I mean, this is the beauty of it.
We don't have all the answers.
Uh, we spent an inordinate amount of
time trying to get a demo together.
Cause I know if anyone,
anyone listening to this is probably
scratching their head, like
how the, what the, huh?
So I'm going to post this
PDF on podcast index.social.
And so, uh, when we put the
show up so people can see that,
and if you guys can hang on,
uh, then we'd like to
guide you through, uh,
get you up and running so you can
take a look at this in action.
How does that sound?
Sounds great.
Yeah.
All right.
Uh, Tom, Kevin, the buzzsprouters.
Thank you so much for being
with us on, uh, this, uh,
seminal episode of podcasting 2.0 episode
number 10, Dave, thank you for coming
from your deathbed and your airlock.
I know that you've, how
long will you be continued
to be quarantined there
another week or so?
I'm going to be locked in my bedroom
for an additional five days.
So I'm going to, uh, that's what I was
telling Adam earlier, my, my, the root,
my family's on one side of the house,
there's a hallway and then I'm on,
I'm in my bedroom on the
other side of the house.
So there's like this, it's like this
air, the space airlock between us,
you know, it's like my wife would
drop like lunch into the hallway
and shut the door and it's like, you
know, just, well, could
not be a better time to
start exposing people to
something when you've
got lots of time on your hands, Dave,
like you can just sit at
home on your deathbed and
watch along as it all starts to unfold.
Yeah.
Watching.
That's what I'm good at right now.
All right, everybody, I'm sure we'll
have a lot more to talk about next week.
Uh, again, thanks to Tom
and Kevin from Buzzsprout.
Check them out at buzzsprout.com.
Podcasting 2.0 will return
next Friday and we'll
see if we can push this
thing to yet another level.
See you then, everybody.
Take care.